[Music]
Hi, you're watching Business Central
Launch Edition 2025 wave 2. My name is
Maria Jallesa and I'll be introducing
custom templates as part of this what's
new in AOG for GitHub session. Before we
get started with the content, I want to
share a quote from the AOG Go creator
himself, namely Freddy Christensen, that
says, "Ago for GitHub is a plug-and-play
DevOps solutions for business central
development that aims to cover 90% of
the functionality that 100% of the
partners need. Now, even with such high
ambitions, we do acknowledge that some
teams simply have different development
requirement. That is why we believe that
letting teams customize AOG go for
GitHub allows them to adapt it to their
own needs. This makes development
faster, encourages reuse and helps meet
specific business goals. Be it faster
delivery or lower maintenance. But
actually even at its creation, AO go for
GitHub has always been customizable.
Here we've listed uh several several
ways of how teams can customize a go to
match their own needs. The most common
one is using AOGO settings to customize
certain behavior as well as control the
YAML content behind the GitHub actions
in your own repositories. Another way is
to define your own custom workflows that
complement existing ago functionality.
And the most common scenario we have
seen so far is uh defining and
implementing your own scripts and script
overrides for uh certain processes in
the development cycle. From the 7.3
release of AOG Go, there's actually a
new way to customize AOGO. Namely, this
is the support for adding custom jobs to
existing Aogo workflows. Without going
too much into demo, I just want to show
you how easy it is. It is uh just simply
injecting the YAML code of your custom
job directly in in this case the CI/CD
workflow that AOG provides. I don't want
to spend much time on this because the
gem of this release is actually the
support for custom AOG Go templates. Now
let's explore what it means. For those
of you who already use AOG Go, you
should know that it provides a couple of
templates with various workflows that
support business central development. Uh
these templates you would use to create
your own repositories or to adapt your
existing repositories using the
templates. Uh in the case where the
repositories um point to existing ago
templates uh when you run update AO go
system files the latest updates will be
applied from the original template. with
the support of custom templates, we add
a middle layer uh a custom template
layer that is actually an ago repository
itself and when you update the custom
template, it fetches the updates from
the original uh ago template while when
you update the end repository, it
fetches the customizations that you have
provided in your custom template. Now
let's jump on a demo.
As I already mentioned, custom templates
are actually ago repositories. So in
order to create a custom template, you
need to go to one of our templates. Here
I have opened the Aogo PTE and simply
create a new repository out of this
template. Here you can give it a name.
In this case, I'm going to create a
repository a for custom templates that
matches the Business Central launch
edition demo. Here you can see the
repository is created and the template
is the original one that we used when
creating the repository. Here in the
custom template I have added a custom
job in the CI/CD workflow that is
supposed to run before the build jobs.
Uh it's pretty simple. It's just for
demo purposes. And as you can see the
build job actually depends on my custom
pre-built validation job. Here I have
also added a setting in the settings
file for the custom template and these
settings will actually be propagated in
the end repository as well. Now let's
say how it actually works when we use
the custom template. Here I went to my
personal fork of BC apps as you can see
and I have already updated uh the Aogo
template to point to my custom template
repository. After running update ago
system files, you can see that the uh
settings that are added in the template
repository was indeed propagated into a
new file that holds all the settings
that the template repo provides. On top
of that, you can also see that the
custom job that I defined in the custom
template was also propagated in the
CI/CD workflow in my fork of BC apps.
Lastly, I want to show how a CI/CD
workflow now runs in my fork of BC apps.
As you can see, there is indeed a
pre-built validation job that runs
before the build job itself.
Now that you saw how custom jobs and
custom templates behave, I want to
mention the support that we have
provided and some of the limitations in
that uh process. First, uh we introduced
a new naming convention, namely custom
jobs must be prefixed with custom job.
This is to avoid conflicts when uh you
have jobs in your um custom template
that might conflict with jobs we might
be adding in the future. On top of that,
uh native jobs can depend on custom jobs
and vice versa as you saw in the example
already. And also the output of native
jobs can be consumed in custom jobs.
This is also true for one specific
scenario uh for custom jobs, but that's
uh that's very very specific in the in
the build process. Uh as of the
limitations, I think it's worth
mentioning that AOG actions used in
custom jobs will not be updated when you
run update AOG system files. This is
because sometimes we do introduce
breaking changes in uh uh these actions
and we don't want your jobs to be
affected right away. So that's why for
now we decided that AOGO action should
be manually updated should there be new
versions. Lastly, native jobs cannot be
changed. This is to ensure that the core
functionality that Aogo provides stays
intact. As for custom templates, the
main support that we added as you saw in
the in in the demo is that custom jobs
can be now added to any existing AOGO
workflows and settings can be defined in
these custom templates and those
settings will be propagated to the end
repos that reference the custom
templates. The limitations for custom
templates is that native Aogo workflows
cannot be removed or changed apart from
adding custom jobs of course. Uh there
is a setting unused AOG system files
that can be used to remove uh certain uh
uh files that AOG provides but other
than that custom templates should not be
removing or changing uh native AOG
workflows. Lastly for now nonaoggo files
and custom templates are not updated
when running update AOG system files. We
have actually already received feedback
so we might be changing this in the
future. So stay tuned if there are any
changes in that area. If you want to
learn more about the ways you can
customize AOG for GitHub, please visit
our repository on GitHub where we
created a page where you can read more
about the old ways and the new ways for
customizing AOG for GitHub. Furthermore,
uh here you can find some resources
related to AOG for GitHub. If you have
any idea or questions, please do visit
the discussion stop on our ago
repository. On top of that, we also uh
hold business central office hours for
AOG. So, make sure to check out those as
well. And to stay updated on the latest
and greatest that's happening in the
business central uh community from
Microsoft, please follow us on LinkedIn.
Uh thank you for watching and I hope to
see you on GitHub.